Hi, everyone.
大家好，我是
Google Advanced Solutions Lab
的机器学习工程师，Takumi。
I'm Takumi, machine Learning engineer at Google Advanced Solutions Lab
This is the second half of the image captioning session.
这是图像标注课程的后半部分。
If you haven't seen the first half, I recommend checking it out first.
如果你还没看过前半部分，我建议你先看一下。
And in this video, I'm going to walk you through the entire code notebook
在这个视频中，我将带你详细介绍整个代码Notebook，
帮助你理解如何创建一个非常简单的生成模型。
to help you understand how to create a very simple generative model.
All the setup information
所有的设置信息都写在ASL的GitHub Repo里。
is written in the ASL GitHub repository.
You can find the link in the slide
你可以在幻灯片中或者这个视频的描述下面找到链接。
or in the description below this video.
After setting up the Vertex
设置好Vertex AI工作台环境并clone Repo后，
AI I work bench environment and clone in the repo.
under asl-ml-immersion notebooks
and multimodal
solutions.
Here you go.
看，这里就是图像标注的.ipynb文件。
You can find image captioning dot i Python notebook.
So please open this file
所以请打开这个文件，在这里你可以看到所有的流程和指示来构建
和使用图像标注模型，这些我们在上一个视频中已经讨论过了。
and here you can see
all the process and instructions to build and use
an image captioning model which we discussed in the previous video.
Let's take a look from the first cell.
让我们从第一个单元格开始看起。
In the first cell.
在第一个单元格里，我们自然要安装所
有的依赖，包括tensorflow和keras。
Of course we install all the dependencies,
including tensorflow keras
and here we can find TensorFlow keras layers
在这里，我们可以找到tensorflow.keras.layers，
and installing order layers we need for image captioning model
并安装我们需要的所有图像标注模型的layers，
including GRU, add layer, attention layer
包括GRU、Add层、Attention层、Dense层、
Embedding层和LayerNormalization层。
or dense layer embedding layer now
layer normalization layer.
So let's run one by one
让我们逐一运行。
and in the next cell
在下一个单元格里，我们定义了一些超参数，包括词汇表大小，
some hyper parameters, including vocabulary size,
which means how many vocabularies we're going to use for image captioning.
这意味着我们将使用多少个词汇来进行图像标注。
Or you can find a feature extractor, which means
或者你可以找到一个特征提取器，这意味着我
们想要在编码器模型中使用什么样的模型。
what kind of model we want to use in encoder model.
So in this case, as we discussed in the previous video, we are specifying
所以在这种情况下，正如我们在之前的视频中讨论的，我们指定的
是InceptionResNetV2，这是一个非常经典的基于CNN的模型。
inception resnet v2, which is very classical CNN based model
and all the definitions below
所有下面的定义，包括图像、高度、宽度通道和特征形状都
来自InceptionResNetV2的定义，特别是这个特征形状。
image, height, width channel and the feature shape is coming from
8, 8, 1536 is the shape
8, 8, 1536就是InceptionResNetV2输出的形状。
So let's define
那我们就按照这种方式定义吧。
in this way
cool.
酷，
So in the next cell we're going to load the data
在下一个单元格中，我们将从tfds加载
数据，也就是TensorFlow数据集。
0 from tfds, which means TensorFlow datasets.
So TensorFlow datasets host this
所以 TensorFlow 数据集以
“coco_captions”这个名字托管这个标注
数据集
caption data set in this name “coco captions”
so we can specify this name and the loading data.
所以我们可以指定这个名字来加载数据。
And after loading data
加载数据后，我们可以传递一些预处理函数，
we can pass some preprocessing function,
and here we can find some preprocessing, very basic preprocessing,
在这里我们可以找到一些非常基础的预处理，包括改变图像的
大小或者图像的比例，并返回图像张量和文字说明同时。
including changing the size of the image
or the change in the scale of the image and returning image tensor
and the caption at the same time.
So let's run in the same way
所以让我们按照相同的方式运行。
and let's take a look at
让我们看一些例子。
some of the example.
Here we can see, for example,
这里我们可以看到，例如，一个随机的例子，每
一对图像和文本对我来说都是有意义的。
a random example
and each pair of image and text makes sense to me.
So wide plate with a toasted sandwich,
例如，这个图像的标注是“一个装有烤三明治、薯片
和炸薯条的宽盘子”，以及另一个图像的标注。
chips and fries for this image.
And another caption for another image.
And we have a lot of image.
我们有很多图像。如果你想看另一个例子，你可
以再运行这个单元格，你会看到另一个例子。
So if you want to see another example, you can run this cell again
and you will see another example.
So let's move on.
那么让我们继续。
So since we have text data,
由于我们有文本数据，我们需要以一种
标准的方式预处理那些文本数据。
we need to preprocess that text data in kind of standard way.
So in this cell we add start
在这个单元格里，我们添加了开始和结束的特
殊标记，这也是我们在幻灯片里讨论过的。
and end special tokens, which we discussed in the slide as well.
So by adding this so we can handle this token as a kind of special sign, this
通过添加这些，我们可以把这个标记处理成一种特
殊的符号，这个开始标记意味着句子的开始。
start talking means the special token,
that means the beginning of the sentence.
And in the same way, the end token means the, the end of the sentence.
同样，结束标记意味着句子的结束。
in the same way trainds.map and pass this function.
They let's move on.
让我们继续。
And this is a very important preprocessing.
这是一个非常重要的预处理。
So now we have text data, caption data.
现在我们有了文本数据，标注数据。
So by creating tokenizer, we can tokenize word
通过创建分词器，我们可以将像开始标记、
猫、狗这样的词进行分词到某个索引。
like start token or cat or dog
to some index.
In TensorFlow, it is very easy.
在 TensorFlow 中，这非常简单。
and you can call
by passing all the data or the caption data
to this text vectoralization layer
so it takes some time around 5 minutes in my environments.
这需要一些时间，在我的环境中大约需要5分钟。
So let's wait until it finishes.
让我们等待它完成。
Now it's finished.
现在已经完成。
Now let's try this tokenizer either
现在，让我们尝试一下这个分词器，通过传递一些样
本句子，“<start> This is a sentence <end>”。
by passing some sample sentence,
start token This is a sentence end token.
So now you can
所以现在你可以看到，它是以这种方式被分词的。
see it is tokenized in this way.
And so the here you can find a lot of paddings
你可以在这里找到很多的填充，通过改变这个最大标注长
度（MAX_CAPTION_LEN），你可以控制这个填充的长度。
by changing this max caption lengths
But in this case we are specifying 64.
但在这个案例中，我们指定的是64。
So the order of the captions
所以所有的标注都将以这种方式被填充，直到达到这个最大标注长度。
will be padded in this way
until this max caption lengths.
And in the same way you can see
同样，你可以看到这个分词器的行为，这非常有用。
This is very useful.
Once you create you can apply this tokenizer in different captions
一旦你创建了分词器，你可以在不同的标注中应用
这个分词器，并将文本数据转化为适当的标记。
and convert text data to the token at the white tokens.
And it's nice to create converters at this point.
在此时创建转换器是非常好的。
So here we can find string lookup layer, string look up layer,
所以在这里，我们可以找到StringLookup层，并且
创建了转换器，从词到索引，还有从索引到词。
and the creating converter the from want to index and also index to want.
So we're going to use these modules later.
我们稍后将使用这些模块。
So this is quite useful
所以这非常有用，然后我们可以创建最终的数据集。
and then we can create a final data set.
So this is a very important part.
这是一个非常重要的部分。
So we have trainds.
我们有trainds。
We're going to add additional create_ds function, this function
我们要添加额外的create_ds_fn函数，这个函数，
and as you can see, it returns image
如你所见，它返回img_tensor、caption，这是一个元组，
img_tensor将进入编码器，caption将进入解码器。
tensor caption that this is the tuple
image tensor will go to encoder
and caption will go to the decoder.
And also we are creating Target, which is label.
同时，我们还创建了target，即标签。
And in this function you can find this target is created from caption
在这个函数中，你可以发现这个target是从
caption中创建的，只需将caption移动一个单词。
by the is shifting just caption
in the in one word.
Okay.
好的。
By doing so, we are creating
通过这样做，我们将创建一个移位的caption，也就
是下一个单词，并且我们将用这个作为target。
we're going to create a shifted caption, which means the next word A
and we're going to utilize this for target.
So let's define and apply this function
所以让我们定义并应用这个函数，并创建一个批
处理指定批处理大小，一切都已经准备就绪。
and create a batch in specified batch size
So let's take a look at some of the data set.
那么让我们看一些数据集。
Here you go.
给你。
So you can find the image in this shape and caption in the shape
你可以看到Image shape、Caption shape，以及与
Caption相同的Label shape，因为我们只是做了移位。
0 and level in the same shape as caption because we are just shifting.
So we are padding the shifted part with zero value
所以我们用零值填充了移位部分，看起来不错。
looks nice.
So the next part is model.
接下来是模型。
Most of the model code has already explained
大部分模型代码已经在之前的视频中
解释过了，所以我会很快地过一遍。
in the previous video, so I'm going to go through very quickly.
But if you are not very familiar with that very confident with that,
但是，如果你对此不是很熟悉或者不是很有信心，
then you can go back to the the previous slide and check
那么你可以回到之前的幻灯片，查看编码器和解码器内部发生了什么。
what is going on inside encoder and decoder.
So here in this video.
在这个视频里，我们来快速运行这些东西。
So let's quickly run these things.
So this is the encoder and as you can see we are just in the applying inception
这是编码器，你可以看到我们只是将
inception_resnet_v2应用到图像数据上。
resnet V2 to image data.
And please note that in this case we are freezing the most of the parts of this cnn
请注意，在这种情况下，我们冻结了这个卷积神经网
络（CNN）的大部分内容，因为我们不需要训练。
because we don't need to be trained.
This model, basically this kind of the the backbone is pre-trained
这个模型基本上是使用大型数据集（在这种情
况下是 ImageNet 数据集）预先训练的。
by using huge dataset in this case image net data set.
So of course if you want to the train, fine tune again, it is possible,
当然，如果你想要再次进行微调，那是可能的，但
在这种情况下，我们只想保留预训练的权重。
but in this case we want to you just to preserve the weights
Pre-trained.
So next let's move on to the decoder.
接下来让我们继续讨论解码器。
It is a bit complex as we discussed,
正如我们讨论的，它有点复杂。
and here you can find a lot of instruction about the attention layer
在这里，您可以找到关于注意力层的许多说明，以及
我们在上一个视频中讨论过的解码器的步骤。
and also the steps of the decoder,
which we discussed in the previous video.
to create what embedding and first GRU layer
and attention layer add layer layer normalization
and final dense layer.
So let's define in this way.
让我们按这种方式定义。
So model looks like this
模型看起来是这样的，Embedding层，GRU，
Attention，Add，LayerNormalization，然后是
Dense。
embedding layer GRU
attention add layer normalization, then this.
And it has so many parameters
它有很多参数，在定义解码器和编码器之后，我们可以
创建最终的 TF Keras 模型，并定义输入和输出。
after defining decoder
and also encoder, we can create final model
And as you can see, it has two inputs,
你可以看到，它有两个输入，image_input进入编码器，
word_input进入解码器，输出应该是decoder_output。
image inputs go to encoder
and output should be
decoder output.
Now model is ready, but before running training
现在模型已经准备好了，但在运行训练之前
，我们需要像往常一样定义损失函数。
we need to define lost function as usual.
So in terms of the loss,
在损失方面，我们的模型基本上是一个分类模型，因为解码器
为每个类别、每个单词类别、每个词汇生成了很多概率。
our model is basically a classification model
since the decoder generate a lot of probabilities for each class,
each word class, each of vocabularies.
So we can use sparse categorical course entropy as usual
所以我们可以像往常一样使用
SparseCategoricalCrossentropy来解决分
类问题。
for the classification problem.
But in this case our data is padded,
但在这种情况下，我们的数据是填充的，所
以它有很多零值和很多没有意义的值。
So in order to do so, we are defining this
为了做到这一点，我们正在定义这个自定义
损失函数，然后一切都已经准备就绪。
custom loss function
and then everything is ready.
So let's compile the model
让我们编译模型，然后可以运行训练。
and we can run training.
with one GPU, one T4 GPUs to train one epoch.
So if you want
所以，如果你想增加额外的轮次，这是可以的。
to add additional epochs, it's okay.
You can do that and I think you can get the slightly better result.
你可以这样做，我认为你可以得到稍微好一点的结果。
But epoch one epoch is the enough
但是一个轮次就足够了，只是为了检查它是如何工作的。
to just to check the how it works.
So let's just keep it as one and run training
所以让我们保持一个轮次并进行训练，
等待15到20分钟，直到训练完成。
and let's wait
15 to 20 minutes until it finished that training.
Now training is done, so let's use it for captioning,
现在训练已经完成，所以让我们用它生成图片的文字说明，但在此
之前，我们需要为推理重建解码器，以便手动控制增长状态。
but before that we need to rebuild the decoder for inference
we are creating a model for inference.
So here you can find train decoder GRU
所以这里你可以找到训练decoder_gru，训练decoder_attention等。
train decoder attention and so on.
And compared to the train training model, we are adding
与训练模型相比，我们添加GRU状态到输入输出。
GRU state to its Io's.
For inputs,
对于输入，我们添加gru_state_input，对
于输出，我们添加gru_state作为输出。
we are adding GRU state inputs and for output we are adding
GRU state as output.
in the inference group.
Okay, so let's generate text with this
好的，让我们用这个自定义推理循环函数生成文本。
custom inference loop function.
We already discussed the what kind of the component
我们已经在之前的视频中讨论了它应该具
有哪些组件，但让我们简要回顾一下。
it should have in the previous video, but let's review very briefly.
So first we initialize GRU state,
首先，我们初始化GRU状态，这种情况下只是简单地用零向量初始化。
in this case just the initialize with zero vector simply.
And then here we get image
然后这里我们获取图像，再对图像进行预处理并
将其传递给编码器，当然，是训练的编码器。
and then pre process to image and pass it to encoder.
Of course, the train encoder
and we can get the feature image features
我们可以获得图像特征.
and before passing it to our decoder.
然后在将其传递给我们的解码器之前,
as the first word
and then
然后我们将重复这个整个循环，一次又一次地生成文本。
again and again and generate text one by one.
So a step that looks like this coding decoder, of course,
所以步骤看起来是这样的，编码解码器，当
然，然后它返回很多预测的词的概率。
and then it returns a lot of predictions
out of the word of the probabilities.
So there are so many ways to pick up the actual word the final word,
所以有很多方法可以从词概率的列表中挑
选出实际的词，最后的词，最后的选择。
final selection from the list of a lot of ward probabilities.
But in this case we are pulling the word kind of stochastically
但在这种情况下，我们是以某种随机方式挑选词，以引入一些随机性。
to introduce some randomness.
So it is the these lines of code are doing doing that
这些代码行正在执行此操作，最终选择一些单词，
and eventually picking up some words
and the the bringing it back to the brink bring it back to the word
然后使用分词器将它们从单词Token还原回单词，并追加到列表中。
from the word token by using the tokenizer
and appending to the list.
So eventually we should get some captions.
所以最后我们应该得到一些图片的文字说明。
So let's take a look at the result.
让我们看看结果。
So defined this function and let's call it
定义了这个函数，然后调用它。
so here
在这里，你可以看到这张图片的文字说明样本。
you can see a caption samples for this image.
So this sample image is located in this directly.
这个样本图片位于这个目录中。
Just passing this for the JPEG and the
只需传递JPEG和它返回五条文字说明。
it returns five captions.
a catcher in a field playing baseball
or something like that.
It is not grammatically perfect,
虽然语法不完美，
but still the you can see it is generating the text,
但你仍然可以看到它在生成文本，生成多个文本和生成有意义的文本。
generating multiple text and generating the meaningful text.
And also we can see our model is capturing
我们还可以看到我们的模型捕捉到了重要的信息，如棒球、
接球员或一个人站在另一个人旁边，或棒球场之类的。
important informations like baseball
or catcher or
to another man or baseball field or something like that.
So still, it's not very
虽然不是很完美，但它确实在生成非常有意义的文本。
it's not perfect, but it is generating very meaningful text.
It's very surprising, isn't it?
令人惊讶，不是吗？
So the model is very simple.
这个模型非常简单。
cap image data to encoder and the decoder generate captions
So just by stacking this so we can create this
通过堆叠编码器和解码器，我们可以创建这种非常小的生成模型。
kind of the very small generative model.
Okay.
好的。
Currently there are so many generative large language models out there.
目前市面上有很多生成性的大语言模型。
Of course they have more complex and larger network
当然，它们具有更复杂、更大的网络，并在更大的数据集上进行训练。
and train a much larger dataset.
But the architecture may look similar to this simple model.
但是，这个简单模型的架构可能与它们类似。
Thank you so much for watching this video.
非常感谢观看这个视频。
I hope you enjoyed.
希望你喜欢。
If you like this presentation, you'll find more in our ASL
如果你喜欢这个演示，你可以在我们的ASL Github
Repo中找到90多个机器学习相关的Notebooks，
Github repository with 90 plus immersion regarding notebooks
if you find it useful.
如果你觉得有用，请不要忘记给GitHub Repo加星。
Please don't forget to star the repository.